(bouncy music)
Rob:Hello, gophers.
Hello, gophers.
There's lot of ways to say hello gophers.
Here's another way to say hello
gophers, and I can prove it.
This is an amazing historic occasion.
I'm not used to success so this
is a strange feeling for me.
It's incredible to me that Go has achieved
a level of success that
makes people want to
get together and have
a conference about it.
I think that's wonderful
and I want to thank
the organizers for putting this together,
all of you for coming
and especially the entire
community for making Go
the success that it is.
A lot of factors I think
contributed to that success.
You could argue that it's
the features of the language,
it's the lack of features of the language,
it's the combination. I also think it has
a lot to do with the
design, the way we went
about designing it and how it turned out.
Of course a huge part of it is the people
who worked on it and what they did.
And the passage of time, refining
and making things happen.
Today I'd like to take
a look at that whole
timeline and see what
happened. How Go came to be
and where we are today as
a result of that process.
To do that I'm going to take a look,
a fairly detailed look at two programs.
They're both historic.
One of them is probably
the first Go program most
of you ever saw and the
other is essentially the
first Go program of any
interest that we ever saw.
Both of those are historic.
The first one is the old hello world.
Here's the original hello world.
It was written in B by
Brian Kernighan in 1972.
This is the first hello
world anybody ever saw.
This is what B looked like.
It was an interesting
language compared to today.
It was a typeless, word-based
interpreted language.
Of course it was the predecessor to C,
you can see intonations
of C in the syntax,
but you can also see strange
things like putchar of a
where a is this weird four
character integer by name,
and then putchar of bang
star n as a quoted string.
The question is why is there
a quoted string for new line
but a is four characters.
You might wonder about that.
I wonder too. I have no idea.
Some people think that
hello world came from
BCPL but I asked Brian
about this and he said,
"No," he asked Martin
Richards about it and
Martin Richards said it
wasn't him, it was Brian.
As far as we know this is the
first ever hello world, 1972.
Here's the 1974 hello world.
This is the first hello world I ever saw.
This was in the Programming
in C tutorial, again by Brian,
written in 1974 and came as part
of the Unix v5 distribution,
and you can recognize that
this is C program now.
It starts to look a lot like
what I think, even those
of you who don't know C would
recognize as a C program.
There's printf, there's quoted strings,
there's braces, there's main.
Huge leap forward in 1978, C had a book
and there was a big change between the
hello world there and
the hello world there,
which is it got a new line character.
This is the full source.
For those of you in
the know this is still
missing some pieces.
In fact it wasn't until the
ANSI standardization effort
which happened around '88 that
it started to look more like
the C of today. An include
with an angle bracketed stdio.h
on it is a mark that the
library is now something
you talk about instead of being implied.
This was actually written
to the draft ANSI C.
It hadn't quite been
finalized yet when Brian
and Dennis rewrote the
book for the ANSI C.
There's actually a book
copy, came out in early 88.
It was reworked slightly for later in that
year when the ANSI C
standard was finalized,
and there was actually
a change to the program,
which is the appearance of
void in the arguments to main.
I was standing next to Ken
when he learned about this and
he said out loud, "You've
got to put a void there?"
But you do, you did, and it
was probably the one thing
at the time where I thought
C++ was better than C.
I said C99 it's really C89, I'm sorry.
It's just a typo on the
slide. But this is C89.
Okay, that's a lot of
little hellos. Let's get to
Go which is the one that
we're here to talk about.
Skipping ahead a few
generations of languages,
every language now starts
with a hello world.
That's basically where the world begins.
I guess maybe certain communities
look at it differently
but certainly in this branch
of language hello world
is the starting point of
your learning a language.
The discussions for Go
started in late 2007 and in
early March 2008 we started
writing the draft spec.
There was actually a compiler
already under way by then
just to have a play pen and
Ken was working on that.
It was actually generating C output,
which was problematic because
of various interactions,
but it was good enough that
the very, very first Go
program was written with
that although it was so buggy
and hard to make work that
it almost doesn't count.
But once the specs
started to come together
we could actually write a proper compiler,
generate native code and
it was time to write tests.
The very first checked in
tests included this example.
This is the first hello.go
and it's dated June 6, 2008,
and it looks different
from the hello.go of
today and that's what
I'm going to talk about.
You can see it looks a
lot like it but notice
that for instance print
has no parentheses on it,
it was actually a keyword,
and main was an integer value
function and you had to
explicitly return a zero.
We had no printing mechanism
other than this built-in print,
it's a bootstrapping thing and
that's where it's still there.
I think if it hadn't
been for bootstrapping
it wouldn't be there at all.
By June we decided that
since main was always going
to return, you could call
that the clean return,
so we got rid of the argument to main.
Made it just be a [nil-attic]
function that returned
nothing and when it returns
you get an exit call.
That's what June, but it's still
got no parens on the print.
The parens came a couple
months later in August where
we were starting to clean
up the language a lot,
we wanted to get rid of these
magic words and print became
just a pre-declared identifier
as a built-in function,
not really any special status beyond that.
This version I think actually runs.
That's the first workable, by
today's standards, hello.go.
But we're not done yet. On
October 24th 2008 I checked
in a CL that read, "printf
as we know and love it,"
so from now on we're talking
about the printf version
rather than the built-in
print version hello world,
which is not actually
the test version runs
but it's what I'm going to talk about it.
This is very close to today
except for two details.
One is there's a lowercase p on the print
and there's a semicolon,
but they went away.
On January 15th, 2009
after a long discussion,
I'll talk about more in a
minute, casing went in to
specify visibility and so
capital p came to printf.
For the first day or two that
looked so strange and weird.
We were kind of
uncomfortable, but about two
days later we realized
this is one of the best
decisions we'd ever made,
this case for visibility.
That was a big step.
And this one runs still.
On December 11th, 2009 after
the open source release,
which was in November,
we finally got rid of the
semicolons so this is
the printf hello world
version that we all know and love.
It took us a while to get here.
I've gone through it in
about 5 minutes but there's
really 32 years worth of
hello world refinement.
I want to talk a little
bit more about that,
because there's a lot of
history in that sequence.
I want to make sure you
understand that although talking
about C, and the hello world
timeline starts with B and C,
Go is not just some variant of C,
it's actually profoundly different from C.
We started from C. The first
mail ever between us about
Go was from Robert and started
with, "We start from C,"
but it's got ideas from
so many other languages,
so many other threads of thought,
some original things that
I wanted to make sure that I
made it clear that there's a
lot of influences on the language,
both direct and indirect.
It looks most like C
because that's where the
statement and expression
syntax comes from but
most of the semantics
comes from other places.
The declaration syntax of Pascal;
The [unintelligble] which is
modular, the various modules that
Oberon has delivered something
close to the package form,
although again it's a little different;
Of course the whole CSP
branch of concurrent
programming has a huge effect on Go.
The semicolon rule was lifted
right out of BCPL which most
of you have never even seen
let alone [unintelligible];
The way that methods work is much closer
to Smalltalk than say Java or C++;
My great contribution is the
two magic tokens left arrow
and colon equals, they
came out of Newsqueak.
The iota keyword came out
of APL kind of sort of.
And there's lot of other
languages that were in
the room we're talking
about that influenced
it either because of
ways to do things or ways
not to do things or how
to think about things.
I really don't want you to
think that this is some C thing.
It gets called that a lot
and I think it's a mistake.
It's actually a language
influenced by tremendous,
rich history of languages
but unique unto itself.
Which brings us up to today.
Here's the hello.go that you know.
I changed a couple of things here.
First of I went back
to println from printf,
I'll talk about why I
did that in a minute.
And I also put in UTF8
in an interesting way by
acknowledging Japanese
gophers, there are quite a few.
Are there any Japanese gophers here today?
Yes, good. Okay.
I'm going to break this program
down because it's trivial,
you all know it, you've all
seen it and yet there's actually
a lot of thought behind every
single piece of this program.
It has 16 tokens, you can probably
figure out what those tokens are.
I'm going to talk about every token.
Don't worry there's more
here than you think.
First of all package. Actually
I think packages might have
be the thing we spent the
most time talking about in
the design with Go because
we knew how important it was.
We knew that wrapping up things
into a library in a way that
was controlled and stable
gave you a chance to do things
like solve build problems,
deal with dependency issues.
You had to control dependencies
in order to get the
build times to be fast,
which was critical to us.
We had to make the
packages be clean because
that makes programming at
large possible with lots of
groups sharing code and
working together but without
breaking through the walls
between the components.
You wanted the package system
to somehow express all of the
information needed in order
to build. You didn't want to
have makefiles or other fancy
build systems necessary,
you wanted the Go source to
express what was really going on.
We wanted to make sure that
circular dependencies didn't
happen because that controls
the size of binaries,
the speed of compilation, how
much linking has to happen.
There are no subpackages.
There was a little talk about that,
I don't really remember
what the thinking was,
but even though there are
subdirectories in the hierarchy
they aren't subpackages,
there's no such concept.
Every package is a
unique standalone thing.
We've separated the idea of
package name and package path.
Pretty simple, turns out to be
profound in what effect that has.
The whole idea of visibility
being package-level
rather than type-level,
the way it is say in Java
with public and private
is a pretty big deal
and I'll talk about that more in a minute.
Most important I think,
something that I don't
think most people think
about, you just use it.
Within a package you have the
whole language at your disposal.
This is because the
visibility rules work the way
they do but also because
we made it this way.
When you're writing a
package you're basically
writing a standalone Go
program and all of its
pieces and you define the
boundary of the package,
which is what your
clients are going to use,
but inside all the information
is available to everybody,
there's no so-called information hiding.
As Bruce Ellis once wrote,
"Who am I supposed to
"be hiding it from exactly?
I wrote both pieces."
I think that's actually an
interesting design point,
and of course it came out of
the modular branch of languages
but it's very different from
many of the other common
languages in use today so I
think it's worth recognizing.
Package is actually kind of
special to the way Go works.
The next token is main. Now
this is not the function main,
this is the package main to
me. It's one place in the
whole thing where the C
legacy really shines through.
That word just flowed from
B to C to Go directly.
It was originally called capital
main, I have no idea why.
I think it was my fault
but I don't remember why,
I thought you wanted
that to be capitalized.
Anyway it went away,
so there was originally
a capital main package
and a lower main function.
Initially that's how
program execution began but
what really matters is
it's special because the
main package is the root
of the initialization tree.
It has nothing to do with
where the program starts
execution proper, it's actually
how initialization works.
I'll talk about that in a minute.
Import, import is the next token.
Import is the mechanism
you use to load a package,
it's how you get a
library into your world.
Unlike a lot of other ways
it could be done in Go
we decided right up front,
almost implicitly I think,
that import would be
defined by the compiler.
The compiler would actually do
the work of doing the import
as opposed to say a text
processor or some other mechanism.
We worked really hard to make sure
that the design made it very efficient.
For instance the export data
in a package is right at
the beginning of the object
code for the package so the
compiler only has to read the
very beginning of the file,
it doesn't have to read the whole library
in in order to do the compilation.
We worked hard to make it linear.
I've talked about this a lot before.
This is the notion that
you pull the dependency
information up into the
packages from your dependencies
so that someone compiling
against your package
doesn't have to talk to
the packages you depend on,
it can get it all from
doing the single import.
That means that the number
of files you open when
you compile a program
is just the number of
packages you import plus
the source file itself.
It's also interesting that
you don't import a set of
identifiers, you actually
import an entire package.
The concept of package
being the thing you get
is not exactly unusual but it's different
from the way a lot of other things work.
I'd also like to point out that
there used to be an export keyword.
That was how we originally
controlled visibility. It was
pretty unwieldy and of course
you know what we did to
fix that. But it was there
for probably about a year.
There's actually a CL that deletes it.
That was fun to watch go by.
Then we come to fmt, the string
that is the package path.
This is a very short
package path of course,
it's in the core libraries,
but it is just a string.
It has no special meaning to the compiler.
It was deliberately decided very
early on that the import path
separate from the package
name would be just a string
and the language would not
define the meaning of that
string so that we could
change the meaning or put
interesting information in it
later if we chose to do so.
Of course URLs were what we
had in mind but who knows,
maybe some other mechanism
will come up. There's already
talk about doing versioning
through the package path string.
That was always planned to
be an open thing, it was not-
It was just an explicit decision.
This allows for future growth which of
course is exactly what's happening.
Then the func keyword.
This was a big step from C.
It's actually borrowed
much more from the Pascal
side of things because
that's where most of the
declaration syntax comes
from in rough strokes.
Having an actual keyword
introduce a function
is very different from the C family.
Of course it's very common
to a lot of other languages.
It makes it a lot easier
to parse the language
because a keyword really
starts things going.
When you're going to do
a declaration you don't
have to deal with
figuring out whether it's
a type or an identifier, what's going on.
It's really important
that Go be easy to parse.
It makes tooling easier,
it makes it easier to
understand the programs when
you see them on the page.
It also makes it a lot
easier to have things like
function literals or
closures because the grammar
inside a function body is
a lot easier to understand.
By the way the original
keyword was not func,
it was function, because that's
what it is, it's a function.
And it went away on a well-known date.
This is a mail thread
on February 6th, 2008.
Ken mailed Robert,
[unintelligble] and myself.
"Larry and Sergey came by tonight,
"we talked about Go for more than an hour.
"They both said they liked it very much.
"P.S. One of Larry's comments was,
"'Why isn't function spells func?'"
I responded, I mean why
not, that sounds good.
We already have type and
const, why not just shorten
function down to func,
it will fit right in.
Robert objected a little
bit because he thought
it wasn't important but
he rapidly came around.
I think the next day function got shorter,
so you can thank Larry for those
keystrokes [unintelligble].
The next main token, this
is the function main.
It is where the program
starts executing of course
except it really isn't. What's
important here is initialization.
That happens before main starts,
and in fact the whole story
about how initialization
works in Go had been rattling
around, particularly in
Ken's mind, for a long time.
Before Ken left Bell Labs,
which was about the year 2000
maybe a little before, the
last thing he did to the
Plan 9 C compiler was try
to inject some notion of
control initialization into
the compiler and language.
I don't know if that code
still exists in the compiler
but it was there for a long
time. It didn't quite work.
It's actually difficult
to retrofit into C.
But he kept thinking about it
and when Go started it was one
of the things we wanted to
get right because initializing
your program is very important
to getting it to run well.
It's a trivial point but
a lot of languages don't
spend any time thinking
about it and you can get very
difficult states with
unclear initialization order,
random initialization order
and strange behaviors.
The key point about that main package is
that it is the root of
the initialization tree.
Although it took a long time to figure out
how to do it the mechanism for getting the
dependency tree to be
executed correctly with
initialization turned out
to be very easy to do.
We had a lot of thoughts
about much more sophisticated,
fancy ways to do it
that we later abandoned,
including doing
initialization in the linker.
What happens now instead is
the compiler generates little
bursts of code that execute
the inits recursively,
almost, resolving them
in the correct order.
It's pretty trivial but it
took a long time to get there.
As I said we thought
about it for a long time.
It also has a pretty big
effect on how packages work
because inits are one of the
ways you can get around the
strict requirement that there's
no circular dependencies.
It gives you a foothold for that.
Initialization isn't
talked about much in Go but
it's actually a really
important feature for
how programs are built
that's often neglected.
I folded two tokens together here.
Look ma, no void, we got rid of void.
When you have really good
function syntax you don't need
that kind of crutch. It
was there in C because of
course the difficulties
introduced by the change
to declaration syntax but
it's not [unintelligible].
There's nothing after this parameter,
there's no return value from main,
it just exits when the program exits.
There's also therefore
no arguments to main in
a related point because
the runtime handles it.
It's an operating system
dependent feature so we put
them in the operating
system dependent component.
Put no return value in to make
the function nicer to look at.
It also make the hello world
program shorter, always a benefit.
Although this problem
doesn't have any return
values or interesting
function argument syntax
let me spend a moment talking about that.
We spent a long time and
many versions and iterations
sorting out what function
syntax would look like.
How you specified the arguments,
how you specified the return type.
There were arrow operators and strange
groupings as we tried various experiments.
Finally, I don't remember
the exact order but around
the time that we finally
decided what method syntax would
look like, which was to put the
receiver inside parentheses,
the functions then just became
three parenthetical things:
the receivers, the arguments
and the return value.
It took several months to sort
through that because we're stupid.
Brace. The opening brace of course puts it
firmly in the C family of languages.
We never considered using
white space for indentation.
I just think it's a profound
mistake in programming language
design to have your semantics
depend on invisible characters.
(laughter)
(applause)
There's a reason for that.
I've been burned badly by bugs
introduced by invisible characters
causing changes in things.
Particularly when you combine for instance
Python through SWIG
embedded into C and C++
and various other combinations like that.
It never occurred to us.
We're going to make it a nice,
controlled syntactically
structured language.
There's also no square
brackets. We had a meeting
with Sergey after the meeting
with Larry and Sergey,
several months later. I think
Russ was at that meeting too.
Sergey asked why he had to
type a shift when you wanted to
start a new block, why not
make it square brackets.
He didn't win every argument.
A good point about this is
that there's no newline after-
There's a newline after the
brace, it's not before the brace.
You can't put it before the brace.
This is an unintended
consequence of the semicolon
injection rules which went
in in December of 2009.
As I said that notion, the way that works,
which is that the grammar has semicolons,
the lexical analyzer injects them
for you under certain conditions.
That came directly out of BCPL although of
course the rules were a little different.
It meant that you couldn't put
the brace on the next line.
That was kind of an, "Oh sorry," but on
the other hand we do get no semicolons,
and we also have to choose
where the brace goes anyway.
This forces our hand.
We consider that a win,
and gofmt can fix it anyway.
The next token is actually
inside the body of
the function now which
is the fmt identifier
which of course came via the fmt import.
It is not a coincidence that it's the same
word but of course it didn't have to be,
it could have been a different name.
This brings up the point about readability
that I think's important
to the way Go works.
Again it flowed out of the design process.
Every identifier in a Go program is either
local to the package or it's a qualified
identifier with a dot in the middle.
That is a profound effect on readability.
You don't get this idea
that when you do an
import the identifiers
come into your namespace.
What happens is one identifier
comes into your namespace,
which is the package name,
and all of the package
components are bound to the package name.
That's a namespace or if
you like pseudo-structure.
That means that you never
have to look very far to
figure out what an identifier
is inside a Go program
and that's a really
important aid to readability.
I also should probably point out that this
word is fmt, not format. That's my fault.
I will tell you right now it
never occurred to me to make it
format because I knew that you
were going to type this word,
however it was spelled, in
probably the majority of
all Go programs ever
written because it was the
formatted print generator,
and by the second or
third time you typed it
you knew what it meant,
it did not have to be
the full format word.
There are people who disagree with that.
I respect their opinion and I move on.
(laughter)
The next token is a period.
There's actually a lot of uses
for the period token in Go,
it means a lot of different
things. It could be accessing
a package, a structure,
method call, function call.
Early on I remember
Ken complaining than we
had too many uses of dot
and he wanted syntactically
to have a different
character there to split the
uses for something. It might
have been [unintelligible].
We pushed back, we convinced
him it was okay, he acquiesced.
But it does mean that
when you just see a dot b
in a Go program you don't
actually know what it
means unless you look up
a and understand the type.
You can parse Go without a
type system but you can't
analyze it semantically
without a type system.
That's fine, but it does mean
that you have to understand
what the types are of an
expression to know what it means.
I don't consider that a
problem, particularly because
in practice humans seem to
have no trouble with this.
When they see the dot they know what kind
of a dot it is, it doesn't bother them.
One thing that does come up
here though is that there's no,
what would C would be called
the arrow operator, the points
to operator, because if the
thing on the left side of the
dot is a structured pointer and
the right hand side is a field
name you don't want to have
to type star thing dot field.
We automatically insert
indirection operators
for you in order to avoid
having that operator.
That adds yet another meaning of dot
but one that we're quite happy with,
we think the programs
look nicer as a result.
Println. Notice it's got
[unintelligible] p instead of
the lowercase p. That's
because capitals are there for
export, you all know
that, [unintelligible].
I'd like to talk for a minute
about the design of this
thing though because it's
actually a little bit of a story.
We always knew that formatted printing
was going to be reflection driven.
It wasn't going to be like
in C where you have to
explain the arguments
because that's not type safe.
You have to actually understand the
dynamic type of the object you're printing
in order to safely be able to print it.
Also maybe even more
important, because you know the
type of the thing when
you're printing it because of
access to reflection you
also don't need a format,
so you can actually have
a Println in Go which
you can't have in a more
weakly-typed language.
We knew that reflection would get us
there so Println made it possible.
I think in fact most of the time people
don't use format strings unless they're
formatting a fancy error
message or something.
Print or Println does the work for you.
That's a consequence of
knowing from the beginning,
even before we understood how
reflection was going to work,
which was itself a very
long story, we knew that
that's how it was going to
work so we designed for it.
Println and his friends,
they're all variadic functions.
Go is very strong in variadic functions.
The original form of a
variadic function just had
dot dot dot there which
actually came right out of C,
there was no type on the dot dot dot,
it was always an empty
interface implicitly.
Then one day Russ said,
"Why don't we just make a type there?"
We didn't quite know
what to do with that yet,
of course it turned out
to be a really great idea,
took us a while to get there
but on February 1st, 2010 the
empty interface went on
to the dot dot dot so the
signature of Println became
properly defined then and
the relationship between dot
dot dot and slices became
general and actually quite
powerful and very easy to use.
Open paren, not much to say.
Traditional function syntax,
no messages, no function
application with space,
it's just old school open paren.
Then we have a string. I picked
a string here with unicode
characters in it that says,
"Nihongo," Japanese language.
Pardon my pronunciation Japanese gophers.
One of the most important
things about Go that was settled
very early is that the input
source is defined to be UTF8.
Since Ken designed UTF8 and I helped roll
it out with him you knew it was going to
be a UTF8 language, when knew very strong.
I think it's really important
to point out that we just
declared up front, Go is
a UTF8 language, period.
There's no encoding
question, you're not allowed
to write in some other
language because that
means one thing happens
beautifully smoothly,
that if you don't define that
doesn't work very well at all.
That is this string here,
this thing with nihongo in it,
you know the representation
of those characters in
the source code is UTF8
so it is well defined what
non-ASCII characters look
like in the source code.
It just falls out automatically that the
representation of
strings outside the ASCII
plain is UTF8 characters
in the source code.
It's kind of magic driven, there's
nothing there and yet it just works.
It's hard to explain in a way that makes
it sound interesting but it's true.
I think it's really
important to understand that.
No other language that I
know of actually does this.
I'm sure there is one but all
the predecessors that I know
of certainly did not define
this this way, and so they
struggled with the meaning
of a large character [value].
Then of course there's
the whole question of
what a string is. It
turns out it's an array
of bytes with a couple
of special properties.
The string literals are the
most important part of it.
It was actually one of
the very first things we
wrote in the Go spec, it
was written probably that
first week and it's hardly
changed at all since then.
Every detail of that was understood very
well up front because of course we've
played in this space for quite a while.
If you want to know more
about it, a few months ago
I wrote a detailed blog post
which is probably a better
place to read about it
than have me blabbing on.
Then you get to the closing
paren of the function call.
Of course there's no semicolon there.
The semicolons went away
shortly after the release.
It just made a wonderful change to
the language, we loved when it happened.
I should point out that before then
semicolons were optional
in a very confusing,
hard to understand,
constantly changing way.
We struggled with the grammar.
I think at one point there
were more productions
in the [unintelligible]
to deal with optional
semicolons than with the language proper.
It was really difficult
to sort that out and
one day we just said, I think Ken actually
came and said, "Why
don't we just fix this?"
So we went back to Martin
Richard's idea from BCPL.
Got rid of semicolons by
injecting them in the lexer.
It changed the language a
little bit because you had
to format differently but
I think it was a huge win.
And closing brace. There we are.
That's the end of hello world.
There's a whole bunch of things
I didn't talk about in this program.
I didn't talk about the types very much;
What constants are, they're
kind of magic in Go.
Methods, interfaces.
How the libraries work.
How memory management is.
It was garbage collected
from day one, we never
considered any other option.
Concurrency of course, which is coming up.
Then there's the various tools,
the ecosystem, the community,
the outside world and the ecosystem
that develops around that.
I want to point out that
although I've talked entirely
about the language so far,
the language is central
to this story but it's really
only a small part of it.
It's the entire thing that builds around
the language that makes success happen.
The factors that bring
that success in are,
I think building on history,
understanding through
a lot of other languages, of
years and years of working
in software development
what matters in a language,
what doesn't matter in a language.
The experience that comes
from working for a long time.
The process of design. Almost
all of Go was defined in the
first year, year and a half
or so by Ken and Robert and
myself huddling down, arguing,
debating, disagreeing a lot.
Nothing went in until
all three of us agreed
that it was a good idea and that's because
we all came from very
different backgrounds.
It was important to
understand that if the three
of us agreed it was
probably a rock-solid idea.
I think that's a really
important part of the Go story.
Later of course for us in
the end others came in and
helped us make it much,
much better but I think this
idea that you have a small
team designing it and
not taking a suggestion box
and making things happen
was a huge part of why
Go works the way it does.
Once we'd got to where we
thought it was right, we stopped.
We said, "This is it,
this is the language."
Go version one comes out
and locked it all down.
That's a huge part of the story,
I'll come back to that point.
Now I want to go through a second program.
That was hello world, now we
need to talk about concurrency,
and I think a good way to
do that is to somewhat more
quickly go through the first
concurrent program that
I ever saw period and then
the first one written in Go.
It came out of a paper
written by Tony Hoare in
1978 called Communication
Sequential Processes
and the problem is of
course the prime sieve.
What we want to do is print
in ascending order all primes
less than 10,000 that
uses an array of processes
called sieve and each
process generates a prime,
passes it down to the next
one and there's a chain that
develops of filt processes
that filter out the details.
In 1978 this paper appeared,
it actually showed this whole thing.
Hoare credits David Gries
with this beautiful solution.
I should mention in
passing this is not the
sieve of Eratosthenes,
it's not very efficient,
but it is beautiful, look at it.
This is the original
one. This is the complete
presentation of the program
in the CSP paper. There's
no description how it works,
you have to puzzle it out.
I won't go through it all I'll just
point out two important points.
Everything is in here. There's actually a
big select statement down the left column.
The star is a loop over
all of the sieve processes.
There's an array of
processes which is instead an
interesting idea and it's
fundamentally the same
program that you probably
know but it's just
structured a little
differently on the page.
The other important
point is that there are
no channels in this,
it's a rigid structure.
There's just a fixed set of
a hundred sieve processes.
A hundred is known to be enough
because it's the square root of 10,000.
It's a theory paper, he's
proving a point, that's fine.
But because the original CSP had no
channels this is the best you could do.
It's still an interesting program
but it's not very flexible.
10 years later I had been
futzing around with some of these
ideas for a while and decided
I wanted to play with them
for real so I wrote a little
toy language called Newsqueak.
Tom Cargill wrote the prime
sieve in Newsqueak first.
I think he credited Doug McIlroy for
it but it's a longer story than that.
This one however uses channels,
Newsqueak had channels in it.
So the length of the run of
primes is entirely programmable.
The program is much more flexible.
For modern eyes it's a little
easier to read I think,
even though it's a weird little language.
I will point out that I don't actually
know where the idea of channels came from.
I don't claim I invented it,
I really don't think I did,
but I don't know where I got it from,
it was floating around somewhere.
The later CSP book has channels in
it but the original paper does not.
Anyway Newsqueak had channels.
You can probably read this
program and pretty much
understand what it does.
It's adumbrating a lot of Go's properties.
You can see a couple of key points here.
The left pointing arrow operator
for communication, and the
next slide you can see the
colon equal guy squeaking in.
And keen eyes will also
notice a mk which became
make in Go but that's just
a coincidence, sort of.
This program runs by the way.
It's a very long line
going off to the right.
You should fix that,
Andrew, wherever you are.
But it prints them all.
Jumping ahead, 2008, March
5th. We actually started
writing the spec in
Syndey on March 3rd, 2008.
Two days later Robert said,
"Let's write a program,"
and so into the spec we typed
this version of sieve.go
which I think is correct
but it's very different from
the language today. You can
notice that there are pointers,
an issue that we struggled
with for a long time.
They're pointers to a built
in structure that gets --
They still are, they just
don't look like that anymore.
The operators for send and receive came
from the shell, greater
than and less than.
You can recognize the program
but it's a little different.
One other thing, you'll notice that
main is uppercase, the early days.
Might have been my fault,
I think I was typing.
You can recognize it, you
can actually understand this
program in modern Go terms and
translate it pretty easily.
It mutated quickly. In July
we decided that greater than,
less than didn't work
because it was confusing to
have unary operators and
then binary ones with
a completely different
meaning, so we changed them to
be these weird little funny
sort of pseudo-arrows.
That helped a little bit.
Channels were still the
pointers but at least we got
rid of the capital on main.
It's a little closer to current
Go but it's still kind of weird.
Then about a month after that
there was a discussion where
Newsqueak's operator came
it. It got a lot nicer.
We now had prefix arrow for
receive, infix for send.
Channels were still pointers
though so there's still some
confusion about how you make
a channel and what it does,
but you can still see
the change happening.
Notice that, for instance, chan is a
new chan int here, rather than a make.
Early January 2009 we
finally figured this out.
We split new into new and make.
The things that were pointers
to built in structures were
called make so channels
were made rather than newed.
Some people still struggle with
that concept. I don't think
it's hard but it is clunky,
I admit, but it does the job.
The code however is wrong in
this example, this is out of
the spec on that day because
there's still a star left and
the channel types on the
filter function are completely
garbage. We didn't run it
because, again, we were idiots.
This doesn't work.
Just before the release I finally said,
"You know, we should probably make sure
"the sieve program
actually runs in the spec."
I went through and sure
enough it was broken.
The capitalization now is gone.
I brought in fmt. This guy actually runs.
This is modern go except for
the semicolons which went
away on December 10th, 2009
in the great semicolon purge.
This is the program that you can recognize
it all the way back to Newsqueak, really.
It mutated very slightly but
converged really quickly.
The piece that's important
here is that the historical
refinement through languages,
through thinking about the
ideas that are there is
again this process of history
and decision process and
time to get us to here.
This beautiful solution was contributed
by a decades-long process of design.
One thing I did not discuss that's
extremely important to Go is select.
A lot of people read about
Go or knew about concurrency
from other languages and will
play in their language of
choice and implement channels
and coroutines and say,
"Look, it's Go-like." It's not.
If you don't have select
you don't have concurrency.
You don't have real concurrency,
because [unintelligible] for channels.
Without select all you can
build is linear structures.
You can't build the
interesting trees and loops
and other complex structures
which are the key to
building true systems
that use concurrency well.
Also I'd like to point out
that select is the only
part that's really hard.
Everything else is easy.
Channels are just queues,
what's the big deal.
Select though, that's tricky to get right.
It's also tricky to design right.
Go's select again was
the process of refinement
through a series of predecessor languages
originating with CSP to
get the semantics right
and in Go we specced it
out on March 26th 2008.
At that point we knew some of
the things that needed to be
fixed for the select in Go
included making sure it could be
implemented efficiently,
making sure it scaled right,
getting rid of some of the
features of select from other
languages that were nice
to use but made things too
complicated or too hard
to make highly efficient.
That aside, the sieve program
that I just showed you from
2009 is exactly the same as
the one in the spec today.
That's almost five years
with no changes whatsoever.
Open sources systems are
usually not that stable.
They get tweaked and worked,
certainly once they're used,
they're always being adapted, changing.
That's a good thing because
you can make them better but
I think it's important to
recognize that one of Go's key
elements of success was stopping
the change at some point.
We just said, "Go's done well
enough now. It's not perfect,
"it's still got a lot of
problems. We know we screwed up a
"bunch of things but it's better
to just say we're done than
"to say we'll fix that and keep
breaking people's programs."
It's a really important
reason for Go's success.
This is the trends graph from
trends.google.com for the keyword golang.
Down the bottom those two
dates are 2011 and 2013.
Go 1.0 came out in
mid-2012 and I think you
can see there's a distinct
bend in the curve.
It got suddenly much steeper
when Go one came out.
I think that's evidence
that people really need that
stability in order to trust
that they can use this system
and make something out of it.
It's a really important point.
Looking back, what are the
factors for Go's success?
I'm obviously biased. I was in the middle.
I don't know why you guys
like it. I know why I like it.
I can take a guess at what matters.
The features and tools
are obviously important.
Everybody talks about how great
gofmt is and things like that,
that the concurrency is a huge draw.
Having a nice statically-typed
language where nice
and statically-typed don't
often go together is nice.
The concurrency is a huge
win, people love that.
It's also I think one of the draws that
brings people in for the first time.
Having a strictly garbage
collected language
has its issues, there's
no question about it,
but it makes the language
very attractive to start in.
The compiler is fast, the
binary is running quickly.
The notion of static type and dynamic
feel that we tried to get right.
Having a really good standard
library but limiting what
it is so outsiders can bring
in more stuff, we don't
have to put everything in
the core. Works really well.
The tools are critical. The go command,
gofix, gofmt, things like that.
But also the factors which
were part of the design process
all along to make sure
those tools could be built.
That the grammar is easy
to parse, fast to compile.
That the language doesn't
have fancy semantics.
That it's easy to read,
easy to understand,
easy to translate. Those are
all important factors too.
I mentioned gofmt many times.
This other concept which I talked about in
the splash talk a year or so ago that Go
was always designed for Google internally.
We're a big company with
a lot of programmers
and we want to make sure that the language
works for large teams
working on large programs.
That's an intangible thing
but I think Go has a lot
of features, or lack
thereof, or design elements
to make sure that programming
large really works.
Less obvious than those
things I just listed
is the process by which Go came to be.
We started with the idea
that we needed a language
to make it easier for
us to get our jobs done,
and our job is writing server software.
We stayed and focused on
that idea. We're trying
to solve the problem of
writing server software.
There's this process we
went through of concentrated
development, really intense
for several years followed
by a freeze. We planned for
the freeze, we worked hard
to get there but then we
stopped, the language is done.
That was a huge, concentrated effort.
Understanding and really
being involved but
then saying knowing when
to stop is important.
This idea that it was a
consensus driven design
by a very small team
is not unusual exactly
but it's not how everything gets built.
It really is important to the
clarity of the vision the language.
Then of course we went open source.
We got incredibly important
contributions from the
community, a community that
I'm happy to say seems to
get what this is all about
and appreciate what it's for.
Go wouldn't be anywhere
if it wasn't for you guys.
The consequence of all this
is we've got this really rich
ecosystem of externally
provided libraries and tools.
The port to Windows was done entirely in
the open source world, that's fantastic.
That's a consequence of all of
these other things tying together.
In other words Go succeeds because there's
an open source community
that understands our
mission and helps us
achieve what we want to do,
which is to build something
good for today's world.
That brings me to my final point here
which is what I call fitness to purpose.
In March, a month ago, this
guy Donnie Berkholz, maybe he's
here, I don't know, wrote this
article on RedMonk entitled,
"Go:the emerging language
of cloud infrastructure."
The emerging part is cool, I love that,
but if you drop that it would say,
"Go:the language of cloud infrastructure."
That doesn't really surprise me because Go
was designed to be a language
for cloud infrastructure,
that's why we did it.
That was the whole point.
We used to call those things servers,
now it's called cloud infrastructure.
It will be called
something else next year.
(laughter)
That's what we did. I think
he did write a really nice
article about why Go is
succeeding and defining that it
is succeeding. He's got this
lovely little graph here.
Again it shows that distinct
kink in the curve and very
steep lines to the right which
I think is very encouraging.
That brings us to the next
phase, which is the future,
and that's where you guys come in.
We're passing the torch off
to the open source community.
Make something exciting
happen. Thank you very much.
(applause)
Q&A? Do we have questions?
Time for questions, okay.
Does anyone have any questions?
There's a microphone roaming.
Audience:Are there any
plans for a debugger?
Rob:There are plans for
a debugger but they're
very sketchy. It's hard
because the operating
systems today don't want
you to write a debugger.
(laughter)
I'm serious, it's really hard.
We're playing around but I
can't promise anything because
it might fail. We're trying,
we've got some ideas.
Audience:I have a pair of questions here.
The first one is having Go
be a target for embedded use.
Obviously there's some operating
system issues around that.
The second is supporting DSOs or
DLL kind of shared object support.
Rob:They're closely related.
We never expected Go to
be an embedded language.
It's got serious problems because it
needs a fairly large heap to work well.
The binaries aren't very
small because of all
the type information they need at runtime.
It might work in- I mean modern
embedded machines are enormous
so it can be done. You can
run Go as NDK on Android.
But it's clear that we
have to do something
about DLLs in order to
make this world work.
There is effort underway in
the open source community.
It's not clear where
it's going, whether it's
the right answer, what's going to happen.
But for things like Android
I think something has
to happen and we're
trying to make it happen.
For the general question of embedded it
depends what you want,
what exactly you need.
In some situation it might
be a financer. It's never
going to be a real-time
language, so I don't know yet.
It wasn't the design so it's
always going to be a weird fit.
It wasn't the intent.
Audience:First of all thank
you for the awesome language.
After you deprecated net
chan is there a first class
replacement for that, have
you come up with that yet?
Rob:I would love something like that.
The original thinking around
channels for about two days it
was trying to make them coupled
to the network directly.
We kind of gave up on that. And there was
discussion about trying
to have types flow through
channels and that didn't
work out, so we backed down.
There are a lot of issues with
doing channels over the network.
It's very difficult to get
the synchronous semantics,
for instance. They pretty
much have to be asynchronous.
That's a good thing and a bad
thing. Erlang works really
well but they only have
asynchronous message passing.
There's a talk, I think in
this session, anyway sometime
today about someone who's tried
to play around in that game.
He's done some work in the
runtime to support that.
I have sketched out about
20 different ways of doing
it but haven't implemented
any more of them. One day.
I think you need a little
more power from the language
in order to make it work and
we don't have that power yet.
Audience:Hi. I was
interested really quick.
Going all the way back to
the beginning of the talk
obviously you talked about what
you guys were designing for,
your consensus and all that.
Can you speak to even a little
bit more or give one or two
examples of you personally where
you were trying to use those
other tools and what you
rammed your head into where
you decided that you needed
a new language. What were
the problems you were facing,
what didn't you like and
what were those moments of
inception where you had finally
beaten your head against
the wall to the point where
you said, "Okay, this isn't
"going to work. This is failing
here, this is failing here."
Rob:I've talked a lot about
this before [unintelligible].
We were writing in mostly
C++ and some Java and both of
those languages seemed to
be too ponderous to work in.
C++ you have to separate
dot h and dot c, you end up
writing the type specifications
over and over again.
In the environment I
was working at the time,
the binary I was working in,
builds were taking 45 minutes.
I considered that painful.
When builds take that
long you have a lot of
time to think about what
you might make better.
(laughter)
Java isn't really that
ponderous but its ponderousness
comes in a culture of
long-windedness that's exhausting.
The understanding the error messages from
compilers with a weird
type system are confusing.
It just seemed like we weren't productive.
I'd gone from an environment working with
a bunch of tools that
we built at Bell Labs.
I went to Google and we
built some amazing stuff at
Google and we got it to
work but the actual process
of building it seemed
to be too heavyweight.
The language wasn't helping,
the compiler wasn't helping,
the tooling wasn't helping.
It just seemed like it
had to say the same things
over and over again.
We looked into a language that we could
compile faster and look nicer on the page
and be closer to the way we used to work.
There's no question that
relative to the modern
big languages like C++,
D or Java, Go looks like
a bit of a throwback,
at least to those people
who love those languages,
but I'm okay with that.
Audience:During the language
design what were your
discussions or thoughts about
a macro system so that things
like if error not nil return
error didn't have to be-
Rob:I think the first
mail said, "No macros,"
and that was the end of the conversation.
Audience:Fair enough.
Audience:Looking to the
future are there any
plans for more analysis
and concurrency to be
able to take common idioms
like producer consumer
and special case that
to bypass the scheduler?
Rob:There's two parts to
that. One is the runtime
needs to know, or the
runtime and the language have
to cooperate more to
understand patterns better.
We talked a lot about doing
some things along those lines.
Not too much has happened but
I'm not claiming it never will.
One thing I'd like to be able
to see, it's the one argument
that I think makes the current
type system not quite good
enough is that it's very hard
to write concurrency libraries.
You can't write a statically-typed mux or
a statically-typed fan-in
or fan-out structure.
It would be nice to be able to do that
but I'm not sure the cost is worth it.
We talk about these things a lot but
there's no plans to do anything yet.
Audience:[unintelligible]
Rob:You should have a microphone
so they can hear it at home.
Audience:Corollary to that
you mentioned language and
the runtime working together.
Would the team really be
willing to make language
changes just for special casing?
Rob:You don't necessarily have
to do it in language changes.
It could be that if you write
this it works this way which
is consistent with the current
language but runs faster.
We already do things like inlining
and magic tricks in the runtime.
The language semantics are not going
to change, we're can't do that.
I mean unless Go 2 happens.
Audience:What is the status
on library versioning?
Rob:Go 1.3 beta is cut.
Audience:No I mean dependency
management and then version-
Rob:That's something that
the open source community
is working on, we're not
doing anything about that.
Audience:What is your
philosophy around making
breaking changes in the future for Go?
Rob:It's written down: We won't.
If we're going to break
things, other than for security
issues, which may come up,
it's going to have to wait
until there's a thing that's
not called Go version one
We could call it Go
version two or something.
That stability is really important.
Breaking changes are called
breaking changes for a reason,
they break stuff. We don't
want to break people.
Seems like a sensible things to do.
Any more questions? Where's
the microphone flowing?
Somebody in the front here.
How many of you have your gophers here?
Can you hold them up for me?
I want to see if I can get over
a thousand gophers in a room.
Staff:Derek Collison if you're here would
you go back to the corner please.
Maybe last question? Yep.
Audience:Are there any plans for generics?
(laughter)
Rob:There are no plans for generics.
I said we're going to leave
the language, we're done.
Okay. I think I should probably stop
and let the next speaker come up.
Staff:Yeah, we have Derek on the way.
Staff:You had a last question?
Rob do you have time for one more question
while we work on getting Derek up here?
Do you have time for one more question
while we get Derek up here?
Rob:Yeah.
Audience:Rob, what's the
languages that led you to choose
to do errors the way that
we're handling them now?
Rob:The thing about errors is
that they're not anything special.
They're just values in the
language like anything else.
The thing about errors is they're
errors but they're just values.
You have the entire
programming language at
your disposal when you want
to program around an error.
Since errors are a common
feature of any program you
should have the entire
language at your disposal.
You shouldn't need some special
mechanism like a try catch
or something. You should
just be able to write an
if statement or compare
or print them or whatever.
Errors are not special, that's
the defining point of them.
They're not special.
All right, thank you.
(applause)
(bouncy music)